[SPEAKER_00]: Right, so, today's sutta is Sanyātā 46.6, Kundalīyā, and it says...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, that's all in order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a kundalya sutta and it begins by saying that the Blessed One was dwelling at Saketa in the Deer Park at the Anjana Grove.
[SPEAKER_00]: The wanderer kundalya approached the Blessed One and exchanged greetings with Him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once they concluded the greetings and cordial talk, he said to the Blessed One, Master Gautama, I'm the one who stays around the monastic parks
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha replies that the Tathāgata lives for the benefit and fruit of the true knowledge and liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Master Gautama, what things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the true knowledge and liberation?
[SPEAKER_00]: The seven factors of enlightenment, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the true knowledge and liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: What things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the seven factors of enlightenment?
[SPEAKER_00]: The four establishments of recollection, kundalya, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the seven factors of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Master Gautama, what things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the Four Establishments of Recollection?
[SPEAKER_00]: Three kinds of good conduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kundalini, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the Four Establishments of Recollection.
[SPEAKER_00]: What things, when developed and cultivated, fulfill the three kinds of good conduct?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha says, well, when developed and cultivated, it's restraint of the sense faculties that fulfills the three kinds of good conduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the Buddha begins to explain, from that beginning,
[SPEAKER_00]: How is the restraint of the sense faculties developed and cultivated, so that it fulfills the three kinds of good conduct?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says here, Kundalini, having seen an agreeable form with the eye, a bhikkhu does not covet for it, or delight in it, or generally generate lust for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: His body is steady and his mind is steady, inwardly well settled and well freed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having seen a disagreeable form with the eye, he is not dismayed by it, not daunted, not dejected, without ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then it goes on for all the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having heard an agreeable sound with the ear, smelled an agreeable odor with the nose, savored an agreeable taste with the tongue, felt an agreeable tactile object with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having cognized an agreeable mental phenomenon with the mind, a bhikkhu does not cover for it, or delight in it, or generally lust for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: When Kundalīya, after he has seen the form with the eye, a bhikkhu body is steady and his mind is steady, inwardly well-settled, and well-freed in regard to the both agreeable and disagreeable forms, and then sound, sound, smell, taste, touches, and phenomena, a bhikkhu body is steady, his mind is steady, inwardly well-settled,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, his restraint of the sense faculties has been developed and cultivated in such a way that it fulfills the three kinds of good conduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could see how through perfecting the sense restraint... Obviously, we're going to go into details on how to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perfecting the sense restraint fulfills the three kinds of good conduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in...
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't really need to add much more on the top of the sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you do it in regard to the six senses rightly, and your things on the right level, the three kinds of good conduct will align themselves, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you wouldn't have to then start behaving properly, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how then, the three kinds of good conduct, that you can now discern having being fulfilled on account of proper sense restraint, how could you cultivate them, so that they fulfill things further?
[SPEAKER_00]: Such as fulfill the four establishments of recollection, the satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, here Kundalīya, having abandoned the bodily misconduct, Abhiku develops good bodily conduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned verbal misconduct, he develops good verbal conduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having abandoned mental misconduct, he develops good mental conduct.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is in this way that the three kinds of good conduct are developed and cultivated, so they fulfill the four establishments of recollection.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, let's go through satipaṭṭhānas and then I can address the other questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how are the four establishments of recollection developed and cultivated?
[SPEAKER_00]: They fulfill seven factors of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Bhikkhu abides, maintaining perspective of the body concurrently with the body, or, how it's formally translated, contemplating body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ardent, clearly comprehending, recollected, having removed covetousness and displeasure in regard to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as you can see, in order to practice the satipaṭṭhāna correctly, that requires the fulfillment of three types of good conduct, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: purification of your virtue, of your behavior by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just, you know, keeping the precepts or something and not making any further effort to mentally
[SPEAKER_00]: Approve the things or at least endure them on the right level, you know, on that mental level, when like thoughts of sensuality or ill will arise and similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: What this illustrates is like what many of those short suttas in satipaṭṭhāna saṃyutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think there are like half a dozen of them, one after the other, where it says basically how to practice satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it says, well, you practice satipaṭṭhāna on top of the being established in virtue, being fully... bringing your virtue to fulfillment and purification.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, there is no practice of satipaṭṭhāna unless you would have already
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, maybe not necessarily fully realized Sotāpārthi, but certainly established in your virtue properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just, you know, I adhere to the precepts because the authority laid them upon me, but more like I train in the precepts by body, by speech and the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the core of the training.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very much what the Sutta describes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it started by saying liberation, like complete enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Liberation is predicated upon seven enlightenment factors, which is predicated upon satipaṭṭhāna, which is predicated upon right conduct of the body, speech and mind, which is predicated upon sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, liberation is predicated upon sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a separate thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's like, as I said, even as the Sutta says, it fulfills the next step.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, if you just stick to sense restraint and keep refining the same principle,
[SPEAKER_00]: On the body, speech and mind level, you will be liberated.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could forget everything else in between that this sutta says.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there were cases in the suttas exactly that, when monks and nuns approached the Buddha and all they heard, in terms of instruction,
[SPEAKER_00]: was abandoning everything you know it's unwholesome by body, speech and mind and cultivate everything you know is beneficial by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was enough for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they stuck to it and it would have saturated all the necessary levels to put it away.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, there are levels, there are stages to be discerned in between, but it's not like that when the mindfulness, the satipaṭṭhāna stage begins, you can forget about a virtue and you can forget about a sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simply through practicing sense restraint, you will be recognizing now existing stage of satipaṭṭhāna in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which all points to the fact that if you have not been practicing sensory strength, withdrawal from sensuality, celibacy, the precept, virtue, that whole thing, there is no satipaṭṭhāna, regardless of what modern Theravāda tells you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you'll often hear like, no, no, no, anybody, anybody who has any idea of what body within the body or feeling within the feeling or any satipaṭṭhāna means, any idea you get about it, do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's, that's satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not according to this sutta or most of the other suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, in order to have it applicable to you, you need to work your way towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, unless you are already investing lots of effort in purifying your behavior, your intentions, your body, speech and mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: No amount of attempts at satipaṭṭhāna will translate into actual satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putting aside the whole, like, you know, ridiculous notion of being a form of mechanical technique, let's not even get into that, but even if, say, you're trying to be mindful correctly, not in terms of visuddhimāga technique, you still won't have a basis for it, because the virtue is not there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is the virtue not there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because you're still giving in to your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you still giving in to your senses?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because you haven't
[SPEAKER_00]: Realized, haven't integrated sufficiently enough the value of sensitivity and importance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still think it's optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still think it's negotiable, when it comes to the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's basically a grave error, in terms of... because you will end up spending years of thinking you're practicing, when you're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the virtue is established,
[SPEAKER_00]: When one is pretty much aligned with the right view, in terms of purification from the unbeneficial actions by body, speech and mind, and doing things on the right level, then you can be recollecting, you could be maintaining the perspective of the body concurrently with the body, mind concurrently with the mind, phenomena and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, in order to do satipaṭṭhānas, as this sutta says, and there are other suttas as well, they even more explicitly state, you need to be free from five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not temporarily suppressed, but actually fully withdrawn from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of the same prerequisite like for the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what this, what this passage here, what this sentence means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having removed covetousness and displeasure in regard to the world,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in regard, what is the world?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the world is basically your six internal sense bases, with its six external counterparts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, anything, anything that you can see, hear, smell, taste, touch, think, and background to that, it's the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, you would have steadied your mind in terms of covetousness and displeasure, and irresistance, so you could see what level of training has already been accomplished, so that satipaṭṭhānas are fulfilled, as the suttas say.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely upside down, this idea that anybody can do satipaṭṭhāna because it helps you in this way or that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is also why I say, like, if you come to the level of satipaṭṭhāna now, you know, because the Buddha did instruct this to newly ordained monks,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, monks that have not yet, say, had fruition of the right view and so on, but means they already have left the household life, practice sense-restraint, dwelling... restrained by the rules of the patimokkha, eating once a day, being completely celibate, all these requirements, and then the Buddha said, listen monks, you should do this because it will obviously bring your right view to fulfillment and lead you one way only to liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But somehow, the commentary and modern Theravāda and just generally idea extrapolated that it means anybody can do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And quote those paragraphs to support the ideas that anybody who wants, who declares himself a Buddhist, can start this practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring the prerequisites, even for those, in those very suttas that are being quoted, that they already would have fulfilled.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you are already living fully celibate, withdrawn from the world, eating once a day, dwelling in seclusion, even as a householder, then, sure, try satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Purifying your behavior on the level of the body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, then you could say, well, you could try satipaṭṭhāna now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could start looking into recollecting and maintaining perspective of the body within the body, mind within the mind, because you are seeing citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're seeing the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would have already contained it enough through right behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's usually not how it's taught today, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, anyway, then the Buddha says if you fulfill the four factors of enlightenment... four satipaṭṭhānas, you then bring the seven factors of enlightenment to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if you maybe develop and cultivate that specific aspect a bit more,
[SPEAKER_00]: Within, obviously, the whole arrangement of the previous factors, none of them disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that will fulfill knowledge and liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, Kundalini abhikkhu develops the enlightenment factor of recollection, which is based upon seclusion, dispassion, cessation, maturing and release.
[SPEAKER_00]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: leading you towards nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Investigation of phenomena, energy, joy, calm, samādhi, composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, samādhi is a result of the right practice, of the right build-up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something you just do to get the right build-up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he develops the... and then, finally, he develops the enlightenment factors... factor of equanimity, which is based upon seclusion, dispassion, cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, cessation of attachments, dispassion, seclusion from everything unwholesome, maturing and release means maintaining that sufficient amount of time
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that it leads you to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not... it's not... it's not a... it's not a momentary thing or like a quick in and out or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this way, when the seven factors of enlightenment are developed and cultivated, they fulfill true knowledge and liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, Wanderer Kundalini was very impressed, said, magnificent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as I said, the
[SPEAKER_00]: In the beginning, you could see the pattern, say, the structure of the sutta, and it's pretty much the gradual training, as it always is, as it always has to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sequence of this training is not really optional, as I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Despite what contemporary kind of Buddhism will try to tell you, the vast majority of the suttas
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, all of them, if you read them rightly, but say, if somebody who reads them, who is like neither here nor there, in terms of their views, the vast majority of the suttas clearly outlines what needs to be done and repeats it over and over and over again.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, most of the satipaṭṭhāna suttas in... in that Saṅgīrtana īkāyā, then there's that Mājjhima īkāyā sutta, where...
[SPEAKER_00]: When a young monk was being... talking to a king and then he couldn't kind of instruct him rightly to a young prince and then the Buddha told him that simile about being on top of the mountain and another friend is at the bottom of the mountain and then the friend at the bottom of the mountain can't have the same sight and views as the one on the top.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he decides to climb up and go all the way up, he will share the same view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Implying that you need to start to do this in order to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just from the position of being immersed in sensuality, because that's what it says that prince was like intoxicated with his wives and harems and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like there's no way he could have understood what this monk was sort of telling him about.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in that sutra, the Buddha outlines the gradual training and part of that includes satipaṭṭhāna, which basically quite clearly states when the bhikkhu is like fully established in virtue, withdrawn, impeccable, sīla, sense restraint, body, speech and mind, solitude, then satipaṭṭhāna, free from hindrances, then satipaṭṭhāna can be discerned as another layer that now you can develop on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: That sense of... that term that occurs in Sutta, the fulfillment, as I said, begins from the sense-restraint and it never stops.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense-restraint continues fueling all the subsequent development.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know... the spring that starts from the top of the mountain where the water gathers
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, yes, as I said already, you could say that everything pretty much boils down to taming your senses, which
[SPEAKER_00]: rightly, say, confines and contains your mind and primes it for the training, for the obedience training of that wild animal, as we often talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's like when this when the sutta says, you know, like, oh, he's citta, his mind is steady, in regard to sight, sound, smell, taste, touches and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people think, I must steady the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell me what what I do, what do I concentrate at, on, with, to steady my mind, to make it make it unmovable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not your doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be like, how do I calm the wild animal?
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell me how to pin it down, how to hold it, how to join lock it or something, so it doesn't move.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's still going to be a wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you make it motionless, it's still a wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not going to be tamed on account of that fabricated, as I said, confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you study citta in regard to sight, sound, smell, taste, touches and thoughts by not acting out toward sight, sound, smell, taste, touches and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, that doesn't feel enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people, like, you know, I know very well, it's not like they, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: These meditation techniques and contemporary views are kind of some grand scheme, plan to deceive people.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it just comes out of ignorant mind, naturally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you start the sense restraint, and everybody would, when they studied in the suttas, because it's just more than obvious that it's about that, but it doesn't feel enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the sense restraint on its own, it doesn't feel like it's doing much.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start restraining, but the mind is still wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now it's even worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dukkha increases even more, becomes even more acute.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, so, yeah, okay, so, how do I deal with this?
[SPEAKER_00]: With this inside?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, I'll keep the restraint, I'll keep the virtue, but how do I keep the mind from from making me suffer?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when they give in, basically, to these views, to these tendencies, and end up overshooting the mark.
[SPEAKER_00]: End up introducing technique, concentrations, state of self-hypnosis, oblivion to basically dull the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: But instead, you need to stay with the wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's where the element of faith comes in, because you do have a strong urge to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, I'm keeping the precepts, I'm restrained, but let me now also calm down this animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still don't see the animal for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you're really trying to calm is just rooted in completely your idea... well, your view of pain is averse...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm averse to pain and I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any calming that you do out of that impatient attitude, any technique, any meditation that you do, will be coming out of the wildness of that animal, will be coming out of the craving, will be coming out of sensuality, will be coming out of ill-will, will be coming out of hindrances, as the suttas very often say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of giving in to that, let me calm it, just recognize, hold on, let me review if there is any other, like, form of unbeneficial behavior that I'm engaging with, by body, speech and mind, and let me correct that, and then let me leave that, let me wait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me wait for it to mature towards release, how the sutta would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you recognize, oh, that is already actually confining, containing, steadying the citta rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't need to do anything on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the beauty of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you recognize this, that's the establishment in the virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the aggregate of virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like what I often say.
[SPEAKER_00]: You come to the point of, like, really internalizing, recognizing that, oh, I don't know what I should do, or necessarily always, or I don't know what I might do, but I will know what I will not do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognizing things that won't be done gives you that sense of confinement and... and... and... but positive, sort of, eh... confidence on account of containment of that... of the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't need to, like, oh, let me now, eh... calm, watch my nostrils, feel the sensations, do this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no need for it, because the animal is already relatively calm from how it used to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you haven't been acting out towards provoking sight, sound, smell, taste, touches and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the result of that is, well, the animal is not as provoked.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... that's kind of pretty much... the core of the training boils down to that and remains the same throughout.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, all these other stages
[SPEAKER_00]: that the Buddha introduces here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's obviously, you know, they were visible to him and could have been visible to Kundalini.
[SPEAKER_00]: But often, more than not, they were completely not even mentioned.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it was just purification of the action by body, speech and mind, which obviously includes your intentions now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not allowing the center stage, not entertaining for anything unwholesome, not acting out of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those were... those are the practical ways of studying your citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that citta is steady,
[SPEAKER_00]: When the citta is withdrawn from the unwholesome, from the... when he has overcome, lost the concern and displeasure in regard to the entire world, then what you're left with is the clarity of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you could see body within the body, feeling within the feeling, mind within the mind, phenomena within phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, citta is steady by preventing it to move.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot move accidentally, or like, oh, I lost, I forgot about things for a split second, my citta moved.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your idea of citta moved.
[SPEAKER_00]: You forget things for a split second or longer, citta still didn't move.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you didn't act out of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It moves when you open the gates, and you open the gates when you act towards sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and entertain unwholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, pretty much, that sīla, that training, that sensory strain, that virtue, is your samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is what samādhi is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it just continues growing from there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, maybe to also just like a question like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you say he contemplates mental phenomena and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's a phenomenon in the most... say, in the most practical terms?
[SPEAKER_00]: A phenomenon is literally anything
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter where it appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter whether it appears as a sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, or as an idea, or as a memory, or as a non-defined idea, or as an ambiguous feeling, or...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: In and of itself, anything that can be designated, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize that phenomenological nature of things, as in, they don't exist... like, say, oh, is it that... do these things exist in the world or in my head?
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, well, the thought of the world is already a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thought of my head is already a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether I place it in my head or the world, it will be secondary to the actually arisen phenomenon of the world, the thought of the world, the image of the world, and the image of my head.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how you would transcend both internal and external, in that sense, by recognizing the phenomena are.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much all you can say about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything you can think of, anything you can perceive, to that extent, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if it's... you can't quite put your finger on it, it always sort of slips through, you can't quite define it, it's real as such, as a non-definable, always slipping through thing that you're trying to think.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what phenomena are.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of the seven factors of enlightenment, we could just mention, perhaps, that...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, fulfilling the factor of recollection, the factor of sati, the factor of not falling away from the right perspective, from the right context, no matter what comes to your senses, through animal not being provoked towards sight, sound, smell, taste, touches,
[SPEAKER_00]: You are already staying within the same context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through not acting out towards things that are unbeneficial by body, speech and mind, you are maintaining the right context.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why I said, like, once you start recognizing this, you realize, oh, this is quite good, because it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to do anything on top of it to develop the factor of sati or to keep it together.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must concentrate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, accidentally, I lost it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I lost it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It slipped my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to not intentionally choose to go against the principles that you would have been developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's loads of room for breeding, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, same investigation of phenomena, investigation of the nature of things, as you have to say, especially when you pick the specific
[SPEAKER_00]: Universally, kind of, relevant phenomena, such as tantra, craving, ownership, like all these subtle background things, that kind of, you know, manifest, but cannot be quite coarsely defined, all those things become discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even your own mind, citta, signs of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a form of seeing, basically, citta, the animal, as an actual living phenomenon, that lives neither here nor there, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in the world of the senses, nor in your point of view, but it's kind of there in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: Real as such, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: People can think about the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, for them, they either place it either, oh, it's in my head or it's in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, they already pervert the order by thinking it second to what it actually is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to... and there is no amount of thinking that you can do that will reveal it for you, unless that thinking, it's paired, based upon, comes out of virtue and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's, as I said many times before, that's what creates, allows that new dimension, new perspective, new point of view to kind of be built upon internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, obviously, once the clarity is developed through the investigation phenomena rightly, energy arises, energy brings the joy and pleasure, that results in calm, paśādhi, and that results in samādhi, composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: which then obviously all kind of culminates in the factor of immovability, complete equanimity and dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could see again how completely upside down
[SPEAKER_00]: The modern views are of, well, I'll just pick this composure, the sixth factor, that result, that's kind of predicated on five factors before, and three right behavior, four foundations of mindfulness before that, and three right behaviors before that, and full-on sensory strength perfection before that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just pick the samādhi,
[SPEAKER_00]: And any physical kind of sensations that I would have sort of become familiar and have affinity towards, I'll do that to calm me, to pacify me, and then everything else we kind of re-emerge somehow in retroactively.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, good luck with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think that concludes the the sutta part, really.